"Win-Win Dietary Solutions
to the Climate Crisis"
Scientists have a clear moral
obligation to clearly warn humanity
of any catastrophic threat
and to tell it like it is.
In November 2019, more than
11,000 scientists from 150 countries
clearly and unequivocally
declared that planet Earth
is facing a climate emergency.
CO2 levels are rising, the glaciers
are melting, Antarctica is melting.
The oceans are getting
hotter, more acidic.
Sea levels are rising, and so
are extreme weather events.
And yes, fossil fuel use is
going up, like air travel, but
so is per capita meat consumption.
In fact, one of the solutions
they offer to help the climate
crisis is eating mostly
plant-based foods while reducing the
global consumption of animal products.
And what makes designing a sustainable
diet so easy is that the same advice—
like eat less meat—is good for
both personal health, like reducing
the risk of our number #1 killer,
as well as for planetary health.
The least healthy foods also cause
the worst environmental impact.
The foods with the most nutrition
just so happen to be the foods
that cause the lowest greenhouse gas
emissions, so you get this win-win effect.
So let's put it all together.
If we are to redesign the global food
system for human and planetary health—
which is to say human health and future
human health—what would it look like?
Enter: the EAT-Lancet Commission,
the result of more than two years
of collaboration between 37 experts
from 16 countries, suggesting
a cut in total meat consumption
down to like an ounce a day—
that's like the weight of
a single chicken nugget—
all the while dramatically
increasing our intakes
of legumes—which are beans,
split peas, chickpeas, and lentils—
nuts, fruits, and vegetables,
because we're not just in a
climate crisis, but a health crisis.
Unhealthy diets cause more death
and disease than smoking,
more than unsafe sex, and alcohol,
drug, and tobacco use combined.
But we can address both
crises at the same time
by increasing our consumption
of whole plant foods
and substantially reducing our
consumption of animal source foods.
Eating such a diet could save the lives
of more than 10 million people a year
and may just help save the world.
The Paris Agreement had set
out a boundary condition,
an aspirational goal for a carbon budget
to help prevent catastrophic impacts,
and staying within the
boundary for climate change
can be achieved by consuming
plant-based diets.
And the personal benefits may be
comparable with or even exceed
the value of the environmental benefits.
The healthcare benefits alone
for a healthy global diet—
a predominantly plant-based diet,
a vegetarian or a vegan diet—
could exceed the price
of the carbon saved.
We're talking up to $30
trillion dollars a year saved
from the health benefits alone.
Now if the health of yourself,
the planet, and your own children
doesn't quite motivate you, consider
that you may also be facing threats
to the global beer supply.
And healthier diets don't just
reduce greenhouse gas emissions.
Since livestock production is the
single largest driver of habitat loss,
reducing meat consumption
is also the key
to biodiversity conservation,
ideally, perhaps, reducing demand
for animal-based
foods by increasing
the proportion of plant-based
foods up to like 90% of the diet.
Livestock production is also a
leading cause of soil loss, water
and nutrient pollution. Yet it appears
to be a blind spot in water policy.
Despite the fact that animal products
form the single most important factor
in humanity's water footprint,
water managers never seem
to talk about meat and dairy.
But it's not just animal products.
I mean, yes, at least 80% of
the deforestation in the Amazon
is to raise cattle and grow
feed crops like soybeans
to export to other farm animals,
but also to make vegetable oil,
most of which is from palm and soy.
Both crops have been expanding,
resulting in massive deforestation.
It just seems particularly egregious
if that deforestation takes place
for the sake of junk food.
Not everyone agrees we should
be moving to healthier diets, though.
The World Health Organization actually
pulled out of the EAT-Lancet Commission
because of their promotion of a global
move to more plant-based foods.
See, if we focused on promoting
predominantly plant-based foods
and excluding foods deemed
unhealthy, including meat and other
animal-based foods, such a diet could,
yeah, save 10 million lives a year,
$30 trillion dollars, and help save
the entire planet, but could lead
to the loss of jobs linked to animal
husbandry and the production of junk.